<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book>
  <title>The Origin of Species by means of Natural Selection; or, the
Preservation of Favoured Races in the Struggle for Life.</title>
  <author>Charles Darwin, M.A., F.R.S.</author>
  <chapter>
    <head>Introduction</head>
    <p>
      <s>When on board H.M.S. Beagle, as naturalist, I was much struck with certainfacts in the distribution of the organic beings inhabiting South America,and in the geological relations of the present to the past inhabitants ofthat continent.</s>
      <s>These facts, as will be seen in the latter chapters ofthis volume, seemed to throw some light on the origin of species--thatmystery of mysteries, as it has been called by one of our greatestphilosophers.</s>
      <s>On my return home, it occurred to me, in 1837, thatsomething might perhaps be made out on this question by patientlyaccumulating and reflecting on all sorts of facts which could possibly haveany bearing on it.</s>
      <s>After five years' work I allowed myself to speculate onthe subject, and drew up some short notes; these I enlarged in 1844 into asketch of the conclusions, which then seemed to me probable:  from thatperiod to the present day I have steadily pursued the same object.<s/>I hopethat I may be excused for entering on these personal details, as I givethem to show that I have not been hasty in coming to a decision.</s>
    </p>
    <p>
      <s>My work is now (1859) nearly finished; but as it will take me many moreyears to complete it, and as my health is far from strong, I have beenurged to publish this abstract.<s/>I have more especially been induced to dothis, as Mr. Wallace, who is now studying the natural history of the MalayArchipelago, has arrived at almost exactly the same general conclusionsthat I have on the origin of species.</s>
      <s>In 1858 he sent me a memoir on thissubject, with a request that I would forward it to Sir Charles Lyell, whosent it to the Linnean Society, and it is published in the third volume ofthe Journal of that Society.</s>
      <s>Sir C. Lyell and Dr. Hooker, who both knew ofmy work--the latter having read my sketch of 1844--honoured me by thinkingit advisable to publish, with Mr. Wallace's excellent memoir, some briefextracts from my manuscripts.</s>
    </p>
    <p>[...another paragraph...]</p>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <head>VARIATION UNDER DOMESTICATION</head>
    <section>
      <head>CAUSES OF VARIABILITY</head>
      <p>
        <s>When we compare the individuals of the same variety or sub-variety of ourolder cultivated plants and animals, one of the first points which strikesus is, that they generally differ more from each other than do theindividuals of any one species or variety in a state of nature.</s>
        <s>And if wereflect on the vast diversity of the plants and animals which have beencultivated, and which have varied during all ages under the most differentclimates and treatment, we are driven to conclude that this greatvariability is due to our domestic productions having been raised underconditions of life not so uniform as, and somewhat different from, those towhich the parent species had been exposed under nature.</s>
        <s>There is, also,some probability in the view propounded by Andrew Knight, that thisvariability may be partly connected with excess of food.</s>
        <s>It seems clearthat organic beings must be exposed during several generations to newconditions to cause any great amount of variation; and that, when theorganisation has once begun to vary, it generally continues varying formany generations.</s>
        <s>No case is on record of a variable organism ceasing tovary under cultivation.</s>
        <s>Our oldest cultivated plants, such as wheat, stillyield new varieties:  our oldest domesticated animals are still capable ofrapid improvement or modification.</s>
      </p>
      <p>[...another paragraph...]</p>
    </section>
    <section>[...another section...]</section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>[...another chapter...]</chapter>
</book>
